Tufts Published Scholarship PB
Tufts Archival Research Center
Tufts Published Scholarship
1983 -- 2014
Tufts Archival Research Center
Tufts University
PB
82 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This series is organized into two series: Perseus Project Scholarship; and Tufts Published Scholarship.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains scholarship published by Tufts University faculty and staff members.
Biographical / Historical
Since 1955, Tufts University has continued to expand its horizons. In 1964, in one of Wessell's final acts as president, Tufts opened the Experimental College. The Ex-College, which allows students to take classes not normally found in the curriculum, has remained one of Tufts' most popular programs.
In 1977, Tufts established a five-year joint degree program with the New England Conservatory of Music. Soon after, in 1979, a similar program began with the School of the Museum of Fine Arts. Also in 1979, the Tufts Center for European Studies in Talloires, France, was established in an 11th Century priory. The Tufts European Center began operation soon after.
In late 1979, Tufts made another important addition. In October, the Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine opened at its original Boston campus. In 1980, the Grafton campus, built on the site of a state mental hospital, officially opened its doors.
The last two major additions to Tufts University took place in 1980 and 1981. In 1980, the Sackler School of Graduate Biomedical Sciences, established with a large grant from the Sackler family, opened its doors on the Boston campus of the Tufts School of Medicine. In 1981, at the Medford Campus, Tufts celebrated the opening of the School of Nutrition Science and Policy. The school was the first of its kind in the nation.
Since Tufts College was officially established in 1852, it has continued to grow and expand in new directions. From its beginnings as a small liberal arts college through its expansion into a full-scale university, Tufts has maintained a strong academic tradition and a community feel.
- Perseus Project Publications, 1987 -- 2014; PB.001; 56 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains scholarship published by Tufts University faculty and staff working on the Perseus project.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by first author and chronologically by submission within first author.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - The Perseus American Collection 1.0, 2006; PB.001.001.00001; Crane, Gregory; Jones, Alison
    No abstract available.
    Automatic indexing; Text processing (Computer Science); Cross references (Information Retrieval); Named entity recognition; Text mining; Information extraction; Perseus Project
  - Beyond Digital Incunabula: Modeling the Next Generation of Digital Libraries (preprint), 2006; PB.001.001.00002; Crane, Gregory; Jones, Alison; Bamman, David; Cerrato, Lisa; Mimno, David; Packel, David; Sculley, David; Weaver, Gabriel
    Abstract: This paper describes several incunabular assumptions that impose upon early digital libraries the limitations drawn from print, and argues for a design strategy aimed at providing customization and personalization services that go beyond the limiting models of print distribution, based on services and experiments developed for the Greco-Roman collections in the Perseus Digital Library. Three features fundamentally characterize a successful digital library design: finer granularity of collection objects, automated processes, and decentralized community contributions.
    Digital libraries; Repurposable digital objects; Automated textual analysis; Customization; Personalization; User contributions; Greco-Roman collections; Perseus Digital Library; Perseus Project
  - ePhilology: When the Books Talk to Their Readers, 2006; PB.001.001.00003; Crane, Gregory; Jones, Alison; Bamman, David
    Abstract: This paper suggests directions in which an ePhilology may evolve. Philology here implies that language and literature are the objects of study but assumes that language and literature must draw upon the full cultural context and thus sees in philological analysis a starting point for the scientia totius antiquitatis - the systematic study of all ancient culture. The term ePhilology implicitly states that, while our strategic goal may remain the scientia totius antiquitatis, the practices whereby we pursue this strategic goal must evolve into something qualitatively different from the practices of the past.
    Text processing (Computer Science); Digital libraries; Humanities computing; Classical scholarship; Electronic philology; Personalization; Customization; Language technologies; Perseus Project
  - Perseus: An Interactive Curriculum on Classical Greek Civilization, A Proposal to the Annenberg/CPB Project, 1988; PB.001.001.00004; Crane, Gregory; Mylonas, Elli; Martin, Thomas; Nagy, Gregory; Heinrichs, Albert; Hemans, Frederick; Morell, Kenneth; Marchionini, Gary; Smith, D. Neel
    Traditionally, students of the humanities have encountered barriers in their learning. The primary sources of their studies are often physically inaccessible and difficult to assimilate. In Perseus, therefore, we have begun to use the technology of interactive computing and the dense storage capacity of optical disk to create a vast, highly cross-referenced database of textual and visual information, and to experiment with ways to let the user explore this information. Perseus promotes active learning and, we believe, has already begun to alter the three-way relationship between teacher, student, and source material.
    Greece-Civilization-To 146 B. C.-Software; History, Ancient-Computer network resources; Classical Literature-Computer network resources; Perseus Project
  - Perseus: An Interactive Curriculum on Classical Greek Civilization, A Proposal to the Annenberg/CPB Project. Appendix, 1988; PB.001.001.00005; Crane, Gregory; Mylonas, Elli; Martin, Thomas; Nagy, Gregory; Heinrichs, Albert; Hemans, Frederick; Morell, Kenneth; Marchionini, Gary
    Appendix to the 1988 proposal to the Annenberg Foundation for initial support of the Perseus Project.
  - A New Generation of Textual Corpora: Mining Corpora from Very Large Collections, 2007; PB.001.001.00006; Crane, Gregory; Stewart, Gordon; Babeu, Alison
    While digital libraries based on page images and automatically generated text have made possible massive projects such as the Million Book Library, Open Content Alliance, Google, and others, humanists still depend upon textual corpora expensively produced with labor-intensive methods such as double-keyboarding and manual correction. This paper reports the results from an analysis of OCR-generated text for classical Greek source texts. Classicists have depended upon specialized manual keyboarding that costs two or more times as much as keyboarding of English both for accuracy and because classical Greek OCR produced no usable results. We found that we could produce texts by OCR that, in some cases, approached the 99.95% professional data entry accuracy rate. In most cases, OCR-generated text yielded results that, by including the variant readings that digital corpora traditionally have left out, provide better recall and, we argue, can better serve many scholarly needs than the expensive corpora upon which classicists have relied for a generation. As digital collections expand, we will be able to collate multiple editions against each other, identify quotations of primary sources, and provide a new generation of services.
    Digital libraries; OCR evaluation; Ancient Greek; Text alignment; Perseus Project
  - The Challenge of Virginia Banks: An Evaluation of Named Entity Analysis in a 19th Century Newspaper Collection, 2006; PB.001.001.00007; Crane, Gregory; Jones, Alison
    This paper evaluates automatic extraction of ten named entity classes from a 19th century newspaper, the Civil War years of the Richmond Times Dispatch, digitized with IMLS support by the University of Richmond. This paper analyzes success with ten categories of entities prominent in these newspapers and the particular problems that these classes of named entities raise. Personal and place names are familiar but some more important categories (such as ship names and military units) illustrate some of the challenges that named entity identification confronts as it evolves into a fundamental tool not only for automatic metadata generation but also for searching and browsing as well. We conclude by suggesting the kinds of knowledge sources that digital libraries need to assemble as part of their machine readable reference collections to support named entity identification as a core service.
    Digital libraries; Named entity recognition; Historical newspapers; Automatic metadata generation; Perseus Project
  - eScience and the Humanities, 2007; PB.001.001.00008; Crane, Gregory; Babeu, Alison; Bamman, David
    Humanists face problems that are comparable to their colleagues in the sciences. Like scientists, humanists have electronic sources and datasets that are too large for traditional labor intensive analysis. They also need to work with materials that presuppose more background knowledge than any one researcher can master: no one can, for example, know all the languages needed for subjects that cross multiple disciplines. Unlike their colleagues in the sciences, however, humanists have relatively few resources with which to develop this new infrastructure. They must therefore systematically cultivate alliances with better funded disciplines, learning how to build on emerging infrastructure from other disciplines and, where possible, contributing to the design of a cyberinfrastructure that serves all of academia, including the humanities
    Digital libraries; Cyberinfrastructure; Humanities computing; eScience; Perseus Project
  - eCulture, Cyberinfrastructure, Virtual Research Environments and the Cultural Heritage of the Maghreb, 2007; PB.001.001.00009; Crane, Gregory
    Cyberinfrastructure; Digital libraries; Virtual research environments; Cultural heritage; Arabic language; Language technologies; Perseus Project
  - Philology in an Electronic Age, 2007; PB.001.001.00010; Crane, Gregory; Bamman, David; Babeu, Alison
    This paper considers two questions, one broad and thus more a series of further questions, the other more practical and with a particular suggestion for action. This paper emerges from a July 2002 conference about lexica and few would be willing to argue that classicists could not improve upon the foundations left to us by Liddell, Scott, Jones, and the others who labored on our shared Greek-English Lexicon. But simply because we could improve upon what we already have does not tell us what we should build now. We do not need a better nineteenth-century lexicon. We do not even need the best possible twentieth-century lexicon. We need to develop lexicographic resources to serve non-lexicographic readers of the twenty-first century.
    Humanities computing; Digital libraries; Classical scholarship; Electronic philology; Language technologies; Treebanks; Perseus Project
  - Drudgery and Deep Thought: Designing Digital Libraries for the Humanities, 2001; PB.001.001.00011; Crane, Gregory; Chavez, Robert F.; Rydberg-Cox, Jeffrey A.; Milbank, Thomas L.; Smith, David A.; Mahoney, Anne
    This is an expanded version of an article that appeared in the Communications of the ACM, May 2001 section on digital libraries. The published version is more informal. In this article, we describe the challenges of creating digital libraries for the humanities, based on our experience with a series of heterogeneous projects ranging from Ancient Greece to 19th-century London.
    Digital libraries; Humanities; Perseus Project
  - New Technology and New Roles: The Need for 'Corpus Editors', 2000; PB.001.001.00012; Crane, Gregory; Rydberg-Cox, Jeffrey A.
    Digital libraries challenge humanists and other academics to rethink the relationship between technology and their work. At the Perseus Project, we have seen the rise of a new combination of skills. The "Corpus Editor" manages a collection of materials that are thematically coherent and focused but are too large to be managed solely with the labor-intensive techniques of traditional editing. The corpus editor must possess a degree of domain specific knowledge and technical expertise that virtually no established graduate training provides. This new position poses a challenge to humanists as they train and support members of the field pursuing new, but necessary tasks.
    Digital libraries; Hypertext systems; Corpora (Linguistics); Quality indicators; Perseus Project
  - Document Quality Indicators and Corpus Editions, 2001; PB.001.001.00013; Crane, Gregory; Rydberg-Cox, Jeffrey A.; Mahoney, Anne
    Corpus editions can only be useful to scholars when users know what to expect of the texts. We argue for text quality indicators, both general and domain-specific.
    Digital libraries; Hypertext systems; Corpora (Linguistics); Quality indicators; Document editing; Perseus Project
  - New Technologies for Reading: The Lexicon and the Digital Library, 1998; PB.001.001.00014; Crane, Gregory
    Books, codices, really, have begun to share the stage with electronic documents, a coexistence that is likely to prove as enduring as that of manuscript and print. While electronic documents are still quite new, we now have enough experience to speak with something other than anticipation, whether fretful or eager, about how print and electronic media complement one another. This discussion will focus on one particular reference work: the entire text of the Liddell-Scott-Jones Greek English Lexicon (9th edition 1940) has been available on the World Wide Web since the fall of 1995. Between July 9, 1996 and August 20, 1997, the electronic lexicon was accessed 336,649 times, with usage growing steadily (as I write in August 1997, the lexicon is used more than 1,000 times each day).
    Digital libraries; Electronic lexicons; Liddell-Scott-Jones Greek-English Lexicon; Greek language, Hellenistic (300 B.C.-600 A.D.); Text Encoding Initiative; Ancient Greek; Perseus Project
  - Building a Digital Library: The Perseus Project as a Case Study in the Humanities, 1996; PB.001.001.00015; Crane, Gregory
    This paper outlines some of our preliminary findings in the Perseus Project, an on-going digital library on ancient Greek culture that has been under development since 1987.
    Digital libraries; Humanities; Ancient Greece; Digital objects; Perseus Project
  - Cultural Heritage Digital Libraries: Needs and Components, 2002; PB.001.001.00016; Crane, Gregory
    This paper describes preliminary conclusions from a long-term study of cultural heritage digital collections. First, those features most important to cultural heritage digital libraries are described. Second, we list those components that have proven most useful in boot-strapping new collections.
    Digital libraries; Humanities; Cultural heritage; Perseus Project
  - Clay Balls and Compact Disks: Some Political and Economic Problems of New Storage Media, 1987; PB.001.001.00017; Crane, Gregory
    Computers; Classics; Scholarly publishing
  - Building a Hypertextual Digital Library in the Humanities: A Case Study on London, 2001; PB.001.001.00018; Crane, Gregory; Wulfman, Clifford E.; Smith, David A.
    This paper describes the creation of a new humanities digital library collection: 11,000,000 words and 10,000 images representing books, images and maps on pre-twentieth century London and its environs. The London collection contained far more dense and precise information than the materials from the Greco-Roman world on which we had previously concentrated. The London collection thus allowed us to explore new problems of data structure, manipulation, and visualization. This paper contrasts our model for how humanities digital libraries are best used with the assumptions that underlie many academic digital libraries on the one hand and more literary hypertexts on the other. Since encoding guidelines such as those from the TEI provide collection designers with far more options than any one project can realize, this paper describes what structures we used to organize the collection and why. We particularly emphasize the importance of mining historical "authority lists" (encyclopedias, gazetteers, etc.) and then generating automatic "span-to-span" links within the collection.
    Digital libraries; Cultural heritage; Automatic linking; London (England); Collection development (Libraries); Authority files (Information retrieval); Document design; Perseus Project
  - Towards a Cultural Heritage Digital Library, 2003; PB.001.001.00019; Crane, Gregory; Wulfman, Clifford E.; Cerrato, Lisa; Mahoney, Anne; Milbank, Thomas L.; Rydberg-Cox, Jeffrey A.; Smith, David A.; York, Christopher
    This paper surveys research areas relevant to cultural heritage digital libraries. The emerging National Science Digital Library promises to establish the foundation on which those of us beyond the scientific and engineering community will likely build. This paper thus articulates the particular issues that we have encountered in developing cultural heritage collections. We provide a broad overview of audiences, collections, and services.
    Digital libraries; Cultural heritage; Automatic linking; Collection development (Libraries); Document design; Reading; Perseus Project
  - Hypermedia and Scholarly Publishing, 1990; PB.001.001.00020; Crane, Gregory
    Digital libraries; Interactive multimedia; Hypermedia; Electronic publishing; Perseus Project
  - A Document Recognition System for Early Modern Latin, 2006; PB.001.001.00021; Reddy, Sravana; Crane, Gregory
    Large-scale digitization of manuscripts is facilitated by high-accuracy optical character recognition (OCR) engines. The focus of our work is on using these tools to digitize Latin texts. Many of the texts in the language, especially the early modern, make heavy use of special characters like ligatures and accented abbreviations. Current OCRs are inadequate for our purpose: their built-in training sets do not include all these special characters, and further, post-processing of OCR output is based on data and methods specific to the domain language, most of the current systems do not implement error-correction tools for Latin. This abstract outlines the development of a document recognition system for medieval and early modern Latin texts. We first evaluate the performance of the open source OCR framework, Gamera, on these manuscripts. We then incorporate language modeling functions to sharpen the character recognition output.
    Latin language; Optical character recognition; Document recognition; Perseus Project
  - What Did We Do With a Million Books? Rediscovering the Greco-Ancient World and Reinventing the Humanities, 2011; PB.001.001.00022; Crane, Gregory
    Perseus Project
  - Student Researchers, Citizen Scholars and the Trillion Word Library, 2012; PB.001.001.00023; Crane, Gregory; Almas, Bridget; Babeu, Alison; Cerrato, Lisa; Harrington, Matthew; Bamman, David; Diakoff, Harry
    The surviving corpora of Greek and Latin are relatively compact but the shift from books and written objects to digitized texts has already challenged students of these languages to move away from books as organizing metaphors and to ask, instead, what do you do with a billion, or even a trillion, words? We need a new culture of intellectual production in which student researchers and citizen scholars play a central role. And we need as a consequence to reorganize the education that we provide in the humanities, stressing participatory learning, and supporting a virtuous cycle where students contribute data as they learn and learn in order to contribute knowledge. We report on five strategies that we have implemented to further this virtuous cycle: (1) reading environments by which learners can work with languages that they have not studied, (2) feedback for those who choose to internalize knowledge about a particular language, (3) methods whereby those with knowledge of different languages can collaborate to develop interpretations and to produce new annotations, (4) dynamic reading lists that allow learners to assess and to document what they have mastered, and (5) general e-portfolios in which learners can track what they have accomplished and document what they have contributed and learned to the public or to particular groups.
  - Guidelines for the Synactic Annotation of Latin Treebanks (Draft), 2007; PB.001.002.00001; Bamman, David; Passarotti, Marco; Crane, Gregory; Raynaud, Savina
    This paper presents a preliminary set of guidelines for the syntactic annotation of Latin treebanks, as jointly developed for the Latin Dependency Treebank and the Index Thomisticus.
    Latin language; Natural language processing; Treebanks; Annotation guidelines; Latin language-syntax; Latin language-data processing; Perseus Project
  - The Latin Dependency Treebank in a Cultural Heritage Digital Library, 2007; PB.001.002.00002; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory
    This paper describes the mutually beneficial relationship between a cultural heritage digital library and a historical treebank: an established digital library can provide the resources and structure necessary for efficiently building a treebank, while a treebank, as a language resource, is a valuable tool for audiences traditionally served by such libraries.
    Latin language; Natural language processing; Latin language-syntax; Latin language-data processing; Digital libraries; Treebanks; Perseus Project
  - Building a Dynamic Lexicon from a Digital Library, 2008; PB.001.002.00003; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory
    We describe here in detail our work toward creating a dynamic lexicon from the texts in a large digital library. By leveraging a small structured knowledge source (a 30,457 word treebank), we are able to extract selectional preferences for words from a 3.5 million word Latin corpus. This is promising news for low-resource languages and digital collections seeking to leverage a small human investment into much larger gain. The library architecture in which this work is developed allows us to query customized subcorpora to report on lexical usage by author, genre or era and allows us to continually update the lexicon as new texts are added to the collection.
    Digital libraries; Latin language; Latin language-data processing; Syntactic parsing; Natural language processing; Lexicography; Perseus Project
  - The Logic and Discovery of Textual Allusion, 2008; PB.001.002.00004; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory
    We describe here a method for discovering imitative textual allusions in a large collection of Classical Latin poetry. In translating the logic of literary allusion into computational terms, we include not only traditional IR variables such as token similarity and n-grams, but also incorporate a comparison of syntactic structure as well. This provides a more robust search method for Classical languages since it accomodates their relatively free word order and rich inflection, and has the potential to improve fuzzy string searching in other languages as well.
    Digital libraries; Text reuse; Allusion detection; Natural language processing; Classical Languages-Information Retrieval; Perseus Project
  - The Design and Use of a Latin Dependency Treebank, 2006; PB.001.002.00005; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory
    Digital libraries; Treebanks; Latin language; Latin language-syntax; Natural language processing; Perseus Project
  - Guidelines for the Syntactic Annotation of Latin Treebanks (v. 1. 3), 2007; PB.001.002.00006; Bamman, David; Crane, Gregory; Passarotti, Marco; Raynaud, Savina